There is only one thing which I want to mention
more in a very, you know very, very high level
I do not want to get into the proofs and other
things the guys who did the course last year
actually had a guest lecture from somebody
who works in this field and who was able to
talk about another technique which is gaining
a lot of popularity recently, so he talked
about that in a gory detail in fact it did
some proofs from one of the papers that they
wrote and so on so forth but unfortunately
I do not have the guest lecturer here this
time and was also I mean just I will introduce
you that ideas to you and then if you want
you can read up on those later right but in
some sense.
Whatever we have done so far gives you all
the tools that you need you know it gives
you the basic tools for you to understand
more complex algorithms and so on so forth
so that is the whole idea for me to do this
and if you actually look at the book right
the textbook.
They almost in passing mention all of these
algorithms mean they'll have like one paragraph
saying oh this is how you do UCB and this
is how you do they don't talk about median
elimination at all this is how you do something
else which i will talk about in the next class
called reinforce and they mention these things
in passing and then they say we will build
on some of these ideas as and when required
for the full reinforcement learning problem
right.
So in some sense the book treats bandits as
something that is a necessary evil that you
need to know about on your way to learning
about the full RL problem right.
Given the focus of the book that's a valid
way of treating bandit problems but in fact
it bandits itself is a very, very rich large
literature and it is very active area of research
for a lot of reinforcement learning people.
And this one of the reasons I actually covered
bandits in a little more depth.
Than I used to do maybe a couple of years
ago, right.
So couple of years ago.
I did bandits in like one class, right all
of bandits.
Anyway so one thing which I want to talk about
was,
Thompson sampling which is gaining a lot of
traction now okay, so it is more descriptively
you could call it posterior sampling depending
on which literature reading some people call
it posterior sampling some people call It
Thompson sampling so the basic idea is the
following right, So I am trying to solve a
Bandit problem right and we know that if you
know that the parameters of the Bandit if
I knew all the q stars right I can solve it
very easily right so how what do i do, take
the highest right so what I am going to do
when I do this kind of Thomson sampling approach
is to, take a somewhat a Bayesian way of looking
at these things.
Right I am going to say that ok I am solving
this unknown problem, I am solving this unknown
problem.
But I am going to make some assumption about
the parameters of this unknown problem.
Right so essentially the assumption I'm making
here is about the q stars.
I am going to make an assumption that the
true q stars come from some distribution right.
I will start with some guess for this the
true q stars come from some distribution ,right
so if my if my if I know that my rewards are
limited between 0 and 1 like for like many
of the cases we have been assuming the rewards
are limited between 0 and 1 so what would
be an appropriate assumption for this Q star
distribution...Beta
distribution so people remember beta distribution,
the guys who are in ML, the guys who are in
ML at least should remember the beta distribution
so the beta distribution is is a distribution
that is limited to zero and one right and
it can take all kinds of weird forms right
and ,so this is typically a prior that prior
distribution that you assume whenever you
have.
We are trying to find parameters of a distribution
where the parameter is limited between zero
and one ok so the beta distribution is a very
popular prior that is used.
Like that I make some kind of an assumption
let us say that i do not know anything about
the underlying problem right.
Then what will I assume, uniform right you
can assume a uniform distribution saying that
I don't know anything so my q stars can come
from anywhere so now what do I do and one
way of solving this problem is to say that
given my current knowledge about the parameters,
right given my current knowledge about the
parameters which arm should I play okay.
So that I my reward is optimized that is one
way of thinking about it so what should i
do then i should take each bandit combination
right I should I should say that ok, ok the
probability of it so q star 1 is some value
say 0.3 q star 2 is 0.5 q star3 is something
else 1.2 like that so I have to make one bandit
problem and then figure out okay what is the
best arm to play here and then take another
bandit problem figure out what is the best
arm to play take another bandit problem figure
out what is the best arm to play and for each
of these Bandit problems.
I should look at what is the probability that
this is the true q stars according to my current
knowledge about the problem so if I start
off with a uniform distribution then everything
is equally likely right so all arms I mean
can be optimal all arms can be non optimal
and so on so forth so I basically have to
play at random right but it turns out that
doing this computation can be very, very cumbersome
you can just think about it right I am asking
you to figure out for each arm combination
with what is the probability that the arm
combination can occur right and depending
on the nature of the probability distributions
you are assuming this computation can become
very, very complex right.
So the posterior sampling idea is a way of
approximating this computation so what I do
is the following is very, very simple okay.
I have some distribution over what my q star
values will be I have some distribution over
my Q star values so what I do is I draw a
sample from the distribution.
Right so let us say something like this so
my.
So q star1 I am saying is something like this
right and then, that is q star 2.
That is q star 3 .You have another color okay
ok good four arms because I am running out
of colors.
Right so q star 1 2 3 4 right this is the
current distribution i have so i am assuming
that the true value of Q star lies somewhere
in this range, right and it is most probably
this value but I do not know yet right there
is some uncertainty about what the values
are now what I do is, I draw samples you remember
we talked about drawing samples from Gaussians
and other distributions I draw samples so
I draw a so basically right so, this is basically
my reward.
This my reward axis and these are the probability
axis I draw a sample for that is one this
is another that Is another Right.
So now I have a specific bandit problem where
my Q star 1 is this Q star 2 is this Q star
3 is this and Q star 4 is this so I have taken
this distribution right and I have drawn one
bandit problem from this distribution okay
now I solve this problem duh.. right basically
pull arm three because arm three gives me
gave me the best value here so I pull arm
three now I look at the actual reward I get
for arm three.
Right so I pull on three and let us say that
my arm three reward is that this is the actual
reward that I get for arm three and now I
go back and update this fellow based on this
reward right so what ,what do you think it
should be.
It will become narrower because this is I
kind of reinforcing my original belief that
this is the most probable outcome.
So right this will become my belief now this
is my new distribution now again I try to
sample so the probability that I will sample
a high value for the green arm goes down now
because I when I played the green arm I got
a smaller value so I keep doing this until
my probability is kind of converged to the
true q stars at that time when I sample a
problem from there I will most probably be
sampling the true problem right the actual
problem underlying that which I am trying
to solve this .This is called Thompson sampling
or posterior sampling.
So this is getting a lot of attention recently
mainly because people have been able to show
that this can give you better regret bounds
than UCB right so this can give you better
regret bounds than UCB and therefore there
is a lot of attention that's being paid to
Thompson sampling approaches.
The analysis gets really hairy and in fact
until recently there was no analysis of the
Thompson sampling approach but more recently
there have been several three four years there
have been several papers that they have come
up with new techniques for analyzing these
kinds of algorithms different from what we
have been talking about so far.
Are there round based Thompson sampling approaches?
This is kind of round based right yeah.
We are not eliminating any arms that is what
you are saying right well it turns out that
you do not have to even without eliminating
arms you are getting very good complexity
and typically what happens is after some time
the posteriors become so focused right so
the probability of you actually selecting
the bad arm is gone I mean you do not really
need to do a round based computation there
but yeah I mean there might be a room for
sorry after a few steps yeah I mean yeah this
is possibility so the only thing is the only
tricky part is once you do this kind of elimination
you will have to come back and analyze it.
So you saw how tricky this became right I
mean I gave you the right events to consider
here right but to come up with these events
is the tricky part right so once you come
up with these events it is easy to bound the
probabilities right how do you know that this
is the actual set of conditions that you should
consider right for you to prove the result
so that is the tricky part now once I say
that okay here is a round based Thompson sampling
approach then going and showing that it actually
gives you the guarantees that you want becomes
tricky I mean people just the plain Thompson
sampling without any round based thing itself
resisted analysis for about a decade right
and so, so it's not, not immediately clear.
But there is more interesting result that
have come in yeah so people there is a very
old style algorithm very old class of algorithms
for solving bandit problems called learning
automaton algorithm these are so people know
about finite state machines right all of you
know about finite state machines right you
have a bunch of states and have some input
signals symbols coming and then you jump around
the states and so on so forth right.
So there is a class of finite state machines
called variable structured finite state machines
variable structure automata right and people
have used variable structure automata to solve
bandit problems I am not going to get into
the details of it right so it's and it turns
out that some of what the variable structure
automata algorithms are doing is posterior
sampling right it turns out to be very similar
to posterior sampling and very recently and
earlier we knew results only for asymptotic
convergence of this learning automaton algorithms.
So very recently like late last year October
or November of last year people have shown
that they also satisfy regret bounds they
satisfy the log t regret bounds so a lot of
interesting work that's happening in this
phase and yeah I mean of course you're welcome
to try a round based thousand sampling algorithm
I don't know or you just check on archive
right the rate at which work comes out in
this space there might be something already
out there okay.
So I will stop here in the next class we will
look at ways of solving the Bandit problem
which do not depend on the do not depend on
estimating the value function so everything
you have looked on so far look finds the function
Q right capital Q, so next class we look at
one class of algorithms which do not look
at maintaining the value function and directly
try to learn the probabilities with which
you have to select the arms.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved